E. A. Goldenweiser Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
E. A. Goldenweiser Papers 1911-1952 1930-1945
MSS23010
Goldenweiser, E. A. (Emanuel Alexandrovich), 1883-1953
1,500 items
9 containers
3.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Economist. Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, writings, speeches, and other papers relating chiefly to Goldenweiser's service as director of the Division of Research and Statistics, Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971--Correspondence.; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941--Correspondence.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976--Correspondence.; Eccles, Marriner S. (Marriner Stoddard), 1890-1977--Correspondence.; Glass, Carter, 1858-1946--Correspondence.; Goldenweiser, E. A. (Emanuel Alexandrovich), 1883-1953.; Keynes, John Maynard, 1883-1946--Correspondence.; Rist, Charles, 1874-1955--Correspondence.; Vinson, Fred M., 1890-1953--Correspondence.; Young, Ralph A. (Ralph Aubrey), 1901- --Correspondence.
Organizations
Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (U.S.); Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (U.S.). Division of Research and Statistics.
Subjects
Economics.; Finance, Public--United States.
Places
United States--Economic policy--20th century.
Occupations
Economists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of E. A. Goldenweiser, economist, were given to the Library of Congress by his wife, Pearl (Ann) Allen Goldenweiser, in 1955. An addition was given by Margaret Kamarck, in 1977.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of E. A. Goldenweiser are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1883, July 31 Born, Kiev, Russia
1902 Graduated, First Kiev Gymnasium, Kiev, Russia Immigrated to the United States
1903 A.B., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1905 M.A., Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1907 Ph.D., Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y. Naturalized as American citizen
1907 1910 Special investigator, United States Immigration Commission
1910 1914 Special agent, United States Census
1914 1919 Statistician, United States Department of Agriculture
1919 1924 Assistant statistician, Federal Reserve Board
1925 Assistant director, Division of Research and Statistics, Federal Reserve Board
1926 1945 Director, Division of Research and Statistics, Federal Reserve Board
1946 Member, Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, N.J.
1949 Published Monetary Management. New York: McGraw-Hill Book Co.
1951 Published American Monetary Policy. New York: McGraw Hill
1953, Apr. 21 Died, Princeton, N.J.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Emanuel Alexander Goldenweiser (1883-1953) span the years 1911-1952, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period from 1930 to 1945. The collection relates almost wholly to financial and economic affairs with major emphasis on Federal Reserve Board matters. Correspondents include Dean Acheson, Louis D. Brandeis, Paul H. Douglas, Marriner Eccles, Ralph A. Young, Carter Glass, John Maynard Keynes, Charles Rist, and Fred M. Vinson.
The papers are organized into General Correspondence and Subject File series.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in two series:
General Correspondence, 1919-1952
Subject File, 1911-1952
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1919-1952 (Box 1)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1919-1951 (Box 1)
- Subject File, 1911-1952 (Box 1-9)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, speeches, congressional testimony, writings, and miscellaneous material.
  Organized largely as received.
  - American Monetary Policy (1951) (Box 1)
    - Working papers, reviews, and correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    - Research material and notes (Box 1)
  - “Comments on Research and Policy Speech,” letters mainly relating to Goldenweiser’s speech before the American Statistical Association (Dec. 9, 1943), 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - “Confidential Memoranda,” 1922-1933, and one 1946 paper; Governor’s Conference, 1924; Federal Reserve Board meetings; Open Market Committee reports, credit policy discussions, etc. (Box 1)
  - Federal Reserve Board (Box 2)
    - Banking and currency plans, letters and memoranda, 1932-1947 (Box 2)
    - Glass, Carter, unpublished paper by Glass defending his Adventure in Constructive Finance against Samuel Untermeyer, 1938 (Box 2)
    - Glass Committee hearings, preparation for testimony and summary of hearings, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Government Securities, memoranda by Goldenweiser and others, 1934-1937 (Box 2)
    - Margin Regulations T and U bound volume, short history by Parry, 1949 (Box 2)
    - “Memoranda re Credit Situation,” 1925-1929 (Box 2)
    - Memoranda, reports, statements, etc., 1924-1952 (Box 2)
    - Monetary Policy and Currency Stabilization, correspondence and memoranda, 1925-1952 (Box 2)
    - Open Market Committee, memoranda and reports, 1923-1952; and “Statements by Mr. Goldenweiser,” 1936-1945 (Box 3)
    - “Summary Report on Branch, Group, and Chain Banking,” 1932 (Box 3)
    - Treasury Department, letters and memoranda between Federal Reserve Board and Treasury Department, 1919-1948, and “Treasury Financing,” 1942-1945 See also Container 6, Writings by Goldenweiser (Box 3)
  - International negotiations (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, reports, etc., 1930-1946 (Box 4)
    - “Bretton Woods,” reports and summaries of Bretton Woods Conference, 1944 (Box 4)
    - “Currency Negotiations re Economic Conference, 1933," correspondence and memoranda (Box 4)
    - “Monetary Agreements,” 1944-1945; currency stabilization plans; British loan of 1945; Lord John Maynard Keynes’s speech to House of Lords, Dec. 1945 (Box 4)
    - “Report on European Central Banks,” Goldenweiser’s report on a trip, summer 1945 (Box 4)
  - Joint Committee on the Economic Report (Box 4)
    - Correspondence between Federal Reserve Board and Committee, transcript of Hearings, Dec. 10, 1949 and Mar. 26, 1952 (Box 4)
    - Miscellany, including letters, printed material, notes, etc., 1926-1952, undated (Box 4)
  - Monetary Management (1949) (Box 5)
    - Pre-publication comments, letters, notes, etc., 1948-1949 (Box 5)
    - Reviews, notes, and correspondence, 1949 (Box 5)
  - “Palestine,” correspondence with directors of Anglo-Palestine Bank, 1947-1949 (Box 5)
  - Reserves (Box 5)
    - “Asset Reserves Article,” undated (Box 5)
    - “Gold reserves,” correspondence and reports, 1925-1940 (Box 5)
    - “Material on reserves,” covering letter, 1949 (Box 5)
      - July 13 (Box 5)
      - July 20 (Box 5)
    - “Reserves Plans,” 1948 (Box 5)
  - Transamerica Corp., correspondence and hearings, 1949 (Box 5)
  - Viner proposal, material on article including correspondence, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Writings by Goldenweiser, including articles, course and seminar notes, clippings, and sheets from the Federal Reserve Bulletin, 1936-1952 See also Container 3, Treasury Department (Box 6)
  - Personal and confidential notes, 1936-1942 (Box 7)
  - “Transamerica notes” (Box 7)
  - “Bank holiday,” 1933 (Box 7)
  - “La Politica Monetaria Deglie Stati Unita” (Box 7)
  - Published statements and writings, 1911-1952 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous statements and writings, 1914-1951 (Box 9)